<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Kathleen&#39;s Lab Notebook</title>
<link>https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.433</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>5/2 Meeting with Andrea and Dan</title>
  <dc:creator>Kathleen Durkin</dc:creator>
  <link>https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025/2025_05_02_Andrea_Dan_meeting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Meeting with Andrea Quattrini, advisor for SIFP, and Dan MacGuigan, collaborator who has worked a lot with Nanopore sequencing (MinION and PromethION)</p>
<section id="major-questions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="major-questions">Major Questions:</h3>
<p><strong>Dealing w fungal contamination?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Adaptive sampling?</strong></p>
<p><strong>How many samples can we multiplex?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Ligation vs rapid sequencing?</strong></p>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Smithsonian has a MinION!</p></li>
<li><p>flow cells have pretty short shelf life, so even if other Smithsonian folks have leftover reagents, will likely need to order new</p></li>
<li><p>will need a reference genome, both for downstream analyses and for adaptive sampling</p>
<ul>
<li><p>could also use a de novo genome from sequencing the recent samples</p></li>
<li><p>with very fresh tissue, since the genome is p small, could get close to chromosome level genome assembly with nanopore. Andrea notes though that they’ve had a lot of trouble with assembling coral genomes, possibly due to weird genome architecture.</p></li>
<li><p>So maybe genome assembly could be a bonus if the species we use ends up being straightforward to assemble, but for now we should try to find samples that at least fall in same genus as a published genome. Will be trickier if we’re using octocorals (for the better sequencing)</p></li>
<li><p>Andrea will look at the collections and available octocoral genomes to see if there’s a good candidate.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>adaptive sampling could help reduce sequencing of contaminants, but might be less useful with degraded dna (short reads can end up being fully sequenced before pores have a chance to kick them out)</p></li>
<li><p>Will ideally want 20x - 30x coverage for methylation calls. Can probably look into what coverage v depth we want for methylation calling</p></li>
<li><p>MinION flowcell specs: <a href="https://store.nanoporetech.com/us/flow-cell-r10-4-1-2025.html" class="uri">https://store.nanoporetech.com/us/flow-cell-r10-4-1-2025.html</a></p></li>
<li><p>could try a test run with minion flongle: <a href="https://nanoporetech.com/products/sequence/flongle" class="uri">https://nanoporetech.com/products/sequence/flongle</a></p></li>
<li><p>look/ask around about accessing a promethion.</p></li>
<li><p>With the wash kits you don’t actually run the while library each time, you split it up. SO using wash doesn’t require more library.</p></li>
<li><p>Will need to check seq length/molarity (Smithsonian has the tools for this)</p></li>
<li><p>Expect fragmentation to be an issue. In Andrea’s experience, coral hDNA fragments are max ~1000bp. Should look into how fragmentation could/will affect methylation calling. Could think about a size selection? Should ask folks in meeting next week about their experience</p></li>
<li><p>make a list of things Andrea needs to buy.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="my-to-dos" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="my-to-dos">My to-dos:</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Look more into what coverage v depth we want for methylation calling</p></li>
<li><p>Look into how use of fragmented DNA can affect methylation calling, including any differences between MinION and PromethION</p></li>
<li><p>Looks into accessing a PromethION sequencer at a nearby facility</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Johns Hopkins (Baltimore, MD) has a PromethION, but I can’t find additional details for requesting use right now, because the webpage for their <a href="http://grcf.med.jhu.edu/">Genetic Resources Core Facility</a> is down</p></li>
<li><p>NIH Center for Cancer Research (Bethesda, MD) is close , but it looks like they only allow NIH employees/affiliates to use their <a href="https://ostr.ccr.cancer.gov/resources/provider_details/nih-intramural-sequencing-center-nisc">sequencing facilities</a>. I’d also guess they’re in a lot of tummult right now</p></li>
<li><p>UW has a Nanopore Sequencing Core which uses a PromethION. Note sure if I can request a quote from them without sample details (e.g.&nbsp;extraction method, dna concentration), but they have a table of cost estimates <a href="https://millerlaboratory.com/uw-nsc.html">here</a>.<br>
If I’m understanding the “services” correctly, it looks like it’s $1,210/flow cell and ~$40/sample for Barcoding with Rapid Prep libraries. I may also be cheaper if we want to multiplex 4 or more samples on a single flow cell.</p>
<p>So say we wanted to do 12 samples, multiplex w 4 samples per flow cell: 1210*(3 flow cells) + 40*(12 samples) = $4,110</p>
<p>Optimistically I think we could do it on just two PromethION flow cells: 1210*2+40*12 = $2,900</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>SIFP_2025</category>
  <guid>https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025/2025_05_02_Andrea_Dan_meeting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>5/12 Meeting with OU Lab</title>
  <dc:creator>Kathleen Durkin</dc:creator>
  <link>https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025/2025_05_12_meeting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Attendees: “Bingham, Brittany L.” <a href="mailto:brittany.bingham@ou.edu" class="email">brittany.bingham@ou.edu</a>, “Hofman, Courtney A.” <a href="mailto:courtney.hofman@ou.edu" class="email">courtney.hofman@ou.edu</a>, Lilly Parker <a href="mailto:lilly.parker@gmail.com" class="email">lilly.parker@gmail.com</a>, “Helyar, Sara M.” <a href="mailto:sara.schaal@ou.edu" class="email">sara.schaal@ou.edu</a></p>
<section id="background" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background"><strong>Background:</strong></h4>
<p>Trying Nanopore sequencing for methylation mapping of ancient bear samples (5500 and 2500 years old, from Alaska, bone and teeth). Using a PromethION.</p>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes:</h4>
<ul>
<li><p>Used <strong>Ligation kit</strong> instead of Rapid, because Rapid is optimized for longer reads, have not tried Rapid. Note that they did <em>not</em> multiplex, so they were using the Ligation kit <em>without</em> barcoding. They also had way less DNA than recommended for the kit (&lt;100ng compared to the recommended 1000ng).</p></li>
<li><p>For them, adaptive sequencing was not helpful in identifying the short reads. However, they haven’t tried using it as an depletion step to exclude known contaminant sequences. Not entirely sure how software would respond to the short reads – would it try to reject them?</p></li>
<li><p>Suggest standard <strong>genomic sequencing as a QC step</strong> to identify which samples have the most endogenous content. Could this be done in-house at the Smithsonian?</p></li>
<li><p>In contrast to Dan’s experience (presumably with amplified DNA), they’ve noted their <strong>unamplified libraries are <em>not</em> stable.</strong> With the ligation kit, they’ve (anecdotally) had ~1hr to get a prepped library to sequencing. They would <strong>strongly recommend we stick with the available MinION</strong>, instead of looking for an outside PromethION, because of the risks of library degradation.</p></li>
<li><p>They’ve noted that the <strong>flow cells can be finniky</strong> – differences in number of functioning pores, pores degrade quickly, etc. Wash step helps output but still issues.</p></li>
<li><p>Been observing 5-8X coverage to call methlation with some confidence. They’ve also been working with modern comparisons, and the biggest difference in ancient vs modern samples for methylation calling was coverage. <strong>Haven’t noted any major differences introduced by fragmented input</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p>Biggest issue is that their coverage is spotty – they get no data for some regions and lots of data for others – and that their genome isn’t fully annotated, so they have little context for some of their coverage.</p></li>
<li><p>Size select: They haven’t been implementing for nanopore, but have for normal Illumina. Using Pippin, better with short reads than bead. Does Rapid Kit already incorporate a size selection?</p></li>
<li><p>Sawyer 2024 compared EMseq and WGBS for ancient samples, and concluded that WGBS is better for ancient.</p></li>
<li><p>Overall, <strong>the Nanopore sequencing works – they got data – but it just hasn’t been cost effective for them</strong>. They’re going to be trying WGBS soon. Noted that they also don’t know much about other attempts to use Nanopore for aDNA/hDNA methylation mapping, or about how it compares to WGBS/EMSeq. They’ve heard anecdotally about other labs considering, but there are just no published results (or negative results).</p></li>
<li><p>Note: they were working with very little DNA (maybe 100ng), highly fragmented, and for a species with a large genome (~3Gb, close to a human).</p></li>
<li><p>We may have more success/it may be more cost effective since we have newer/potentially better-preserved specimens, and the genomes are so much shorter. While they were unable to incorporate multiplexing, we likely can with success. Suggested <strong>running a single sample on its own flow cell</strong> first to get a sense of how much output/coverage we’ll get. Flongle for this?</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="takeaways" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="takeaways">Takeaways:</h4>
<ul>
<li><p>Should use Ligation Kit instead of Rapid. Rapid is optimized for longer reads. It also includes “transposase chemistry” which seems to perform some type of DNA shearing, which we don’t want with our fragmented reads.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Native Barcoding Kit 24 is same price as Rapid Barcoding Kit 24</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://nanoporetech.com/support/library-prep/rapid-kits/can-i-use-small-dna-fragments-with-the-rapid-kits?filter=fragmented">ONT reccommends</a> Rapid Kit not be used with fragments &lt;500nt</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Stick with the MinION</p></li>
<li><p>Having a well-annotated genome is important, so keep that in mind when selecting samples.</p></li>
<li><p>Prioritize the QC steps to select samples with as much long-read, endogenous DNA as possible</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Paper on optemizing short-read sequencing using a MinION and Rapid Barcoding Kit: <a href="https://academic.oup.com/g3journal/article/8/5/1649/6028073" class="uri">https://academic.oup.com/g3journal/article/8/5/1649/6028073</a></p>
<p>ONT Document on recommendations for sample quantity/quality: <a href="https://nanoporetech.com/document/input-dna-rna-qc" class="uri">https://nanoporetech.com/document/input-dna-rna-qc</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>SIFP_2025</category>
  <guid>https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025/2025_05_12_meeting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>4/10 Meeting with Andrea</title>
  <dc:creator>Kathleen Durkin</dc:creator>
  <link>https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025/2025_04_10_Andrea_meeting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Notes from 4/10 meeting with Andrea to discuss SIFP fellowship this summer</p>
<p>Action Items:</p>
<p><strong>Tenure dates.</strong> Proposal stated 07/01/2025 - 09/12/2025.</p>
<ul>
<li>This works for Andrea!</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Budgeting and sourcing research funds.</strong> What is estimated cost of project (see <a href="../../../posts/projects/SIFP_2025/2025_04_09_SIFP_planning.html">here</a> for breakdown of sequencing costs) and how will Andrea and/or Steven be supporting with funding?</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Materials and reagents for extraction and QC are largely/fully available through the LAB communal resources, so library prep and sequencing are the only costs.</p></li>
<li><p>200ng (minimum for Nanopore Rapid Barcoding Kit) is a totally feasible DNA quantity. Need to consider though that the DNA will be “dirty,” containing mold, symbiont, etc. Need to consider how to clean up and how much total DNA we need to get 200ng of <em>coral</em> DNA.</p></li>
<li><p>LAB doesn’t seem to have a nanopore sequencing platform, so we may need to send samples out for sequencing. Need to look into how cost will change. Can still be kept low with multiplexing though.</p></li>
<li><p>MinION vs.&nbsp;PromethION?</p></li>
<li><p>Andrea is working with a NOAA scientist, Dan, who is experienced with nanopore sequencing and interested in using it more. Andrea will set up a meeting w him to discuss sequencing options.</p></li>
<li><p>Andrea can fully support with research funding, and will thus be senior author on resultant papers (notify Steven)</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>How/when to begin sourcing specimens?</strong> Does Andrea have an inventory database of some kind so I can begin looking for suitable species and collections dates?</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Focus on dried specimens, since they yield better DNA quality/quantity than wet-stored. Andrea’s been seeing higher DNA yield from octocorals than stony, but octocorals potentially less interesting for enviornmental resilience questions.</p></li>
<li><p>Since multiplexing will likely keep sequencing costs lows, maybe we could do 15 stony and 15 octo?</p></li>
<li><p>GBR and maybe Carribean for sourcing old specimens. Maybe we can just use the same specimens as in <span class="citation" data-cites="connelly_unlocking_2024">Connelly, Catapang, and Quattrini (2024)</span> , since we know many yielded sufficient DNA for sequencing. None are type specimens, so additional sampling would likely be fine.</p></li>
<li><p>museum inventory: <a href="https://collections.nmnh.si.edu/search/iz/">https://collections.nmnh.si.edu/search/iz/https://collections.nmnh.si.edu/search/iz/</a></p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Project timeline.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>likely need 1 week for setup, maybe 2 weeks for first round of extractions/QC. Unsure what the sequencing timeline will be if we have to send it out, but the a PromethION sequencing run takes ~3 days.</p></li>
<li><p>Ideally I’d get a full round of samples sequenced in first 5 weeks, then be able to do a second round (e.g.&nbsp;work out the kinks with the higher-yield octocoral samples, then try for stony samples)</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Extra from 4/10 Lab Meeting, talking w Shelly:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Contact ONT! They may be able to provide guidance on workflow modifications for using low quantity/quality DNA</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://bcmb.bs.jhmi.edu/people/winston-timp/">Winston Timp</a>, works in developing sequencing tech and has done lots with Nanopore tech. Can try looking through his related publications or contacting (can use Shelly as contact)</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://nanoporetech.com/document/adaptive-sampling">Adaptive sampling</a></p></li>
</ul>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-connelly_unlocking_2024" class="csl-entry">
Connelly, Michael T., Mary Grace Catapang, and Andrea M. Quattrini. 2024. <span>“Unlocking the Treasure Trove: Leveraging Dry Coral Specimens for Museum Genomics.”</span> <em>Coral Reefs</em> 43 (4): 1153–59. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00338-024-02525-5">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00338-024-02525-5</a>.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>SIFP_2025</category>
  <guid>https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025/2025_04_10_Andrea_meeting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SIFP Project Planning</title>
  <dc:creator>Kathleen Durkin</dc:creator>
  <link>https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025/2025_04_09_SIFP_planning.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’m meeting with Andrea tomorrow to discuss the SIFP project, so I spent some time researching the Nanopore direct sequencing workflow and associated costs.</p>
<section id="multiplexing" class="level1">
<h1><strong>Multiplexing:</strong></h1>
<p>PromethION and MionION platforms support multiplexing, where DNA is tagged with sample-specific barcodes during library prep, allowing multiple samples to be run simultaneously on a single flow cell. Since flow cells are the most expensive component of nanopore sequencing by far, multiplexing could dramatically reduce the sequencing cost per sample.</p>
<p>According to <span class="citation" data-cites="rubi_museum_2020">Rubi, Knowles, and Dantzer (2020)</span>, while recommended minimum read depth for methylation analysis is 10X, their hDNA samples showed little difference in # of CpG positions for a minimum read depth of 5X and 10X. So our goal should be a minimum of 10X depth, but lower could be acceptable?</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="deng_p646_2024">Deng et al. (2024)</span> used a PromethION for WGS of the human genome and multiplexed 3 samples per cell, incorporating a cell wash to improve performance, and generated 154 Gb of output with a final mean read depth of 12X. This tracks with ONT’s specifications of 100-200 Gb output gDNA reads from a PromethION flow cell. NOTE though that the human genome is *much* larger than a coral genome.&nbsp;</p>
<p>If we assume an output of 150 Gb (150,000 Mb), how many samples could be multiplexed while maintaining minimum read depth?<br>
</p>
<p>Human genome: 3,000 Mb<br>
10X read depth: 30,000 Mb<br>
Sequencing output: 150,000 Mb<br>
Multiplexing max = 5 samples/flow cell</p>
<p>Coral genome: 500 Mb<br>
10X read depth: 5,000 Mb<br>
Sequencing output: 150,000 Mb<br>
<strong>Multiplexing max = 30 samples/flow cell</strong><br>
</p>
<p>Say we want 3 time points (e.g., 100yo, 50yo, &lt;20yo). Probably need a minimum of n=5 for each, so minimum of N=15.</p>
<p>I think we’d easily be able to run all 15 samples on a single flow cell! Since flow cells are only sold in packs of 4, we’ll also end up with extra to do more sequencing if desired/possible.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
<section id="choosing-library-prep" class="level1">
<h1><strong>Choosing library prep</strong></h1>
<p><img src="https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025/images/nanopore_library_prep.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Rapid (ligation-free) library prep kit seems best. Of the methylation-friendly options, it requires the least input DNA (still kind of high though? 100ng?). It also has barcode options to support multiplexing!</p>
</section>
<section id="cost-estimate" class="level1">
<h1><strong>Cost estimate:</strong></h1>
<p>Assuming minimum N=15 on a PromethION, incorporating multiplexing to reduce cost/sample.</p>
<table class="table">
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Item</td>
<td># rxns/unit</td>
<td>Price ($/unit)</td>
<td># units</td>
<td>Total cost</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><a href="https://store.nanoporetech.com/us/rapid-barcoding-sequencing-kit-96-v14.html">Rapid Barcoding Kit 96 V14</a></td>
<td>96</td>
<td>1100</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1100</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><a href="https://store.nanoporetech.com/us/promethion-flow-cell-packs-r10-4-1-m-version-2025.html">PromethION Flow Cell Packs (R10.4.1)</a></td>
<td>1 pack: 4 cells</td>
<td>3980</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3980</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><a href="https://store.nanoporetech.com/us/productDetail/?id=flow-cell-wash">Flow Cell Wash Kit</a></td>
<td>6</td>
<td>115</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>115</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><strong>5,195</strong></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>So estimated cost of library prep and sequencing for N=15 samples on a PromethION sequencing platform is <strong>$5,195</strong>. Note that this could be reduced by a few hundred dollars by buying a 24-reaction library prep kit, but it’s dramatically more cost effective to buy the 96-reaction kit. That also gives us plenty of wiggle room for unsuccessful library prep or sequencing.</p>
<p>Note that this doesn’t take DNA extraction and QC into account. I’ll need to talk to Andrea about this portion since the LAB has some community-available resources and the number of samples I’ll extract/QC will be strongly influenced by extraction success.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-deng_p646_2024" class="csl-entry">
Deng, Wayne Xianding, Monika Sun, Pauline Ng, Premal Shah, Kate Im, and Akash Kumar. 2024. <span>“P646: <span>Development</span> of an Affordable Rapid Human Genome Sequencing Assay Using Long Read <span>PromethiON</span> 2.”</span> <em>Genetics in Medicine Open</em> 2: 101552. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gimo.2024.101552">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gimo.2024.101552</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-rubi_museum_2020" class="csl-entry">
Rubi, Tricia L., L. Lacey Knowles, and Ben Dantzer. 2020. <span>“Museum Epigenomics: <span>Characterizing</span> Cytosine Methylation in Historic Museum Specimens.”</span> <em>Molecular Ecology Resources</em> 20 (5): 1161–70. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/1755-0998.13115">https://doi.org/10.1111/1755-0998.13115</a>.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>SIFP_2025</category>
  <guid>https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/posts/projects/SIFP_2025/2025_04_09_SIFP_planning.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
